<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>vdwees.github.io</title><link>https://vdwees.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on vdwees.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 12:52:38 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vdwees.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>bicitrilladora: a one-of-a-kind contraption</title><link>https://vdwees.github.io/post/bicitrilladora/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 12:52:38 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://vdwees.github.io/post/bicitrilladora/</guid><description>
&lt;p>One summer when I was too inexperienced an engineer to find a real internship,
I ended up with a volunteer position working at a non-profit working under a
Nicaraguan engineer. Needless to say, the summer was an eventful one and I
have many good memories and stories from that summer. One of my favorite
projects was the design and construction of the &amp;ldquo;bicitrilladora&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="some-background">Some Background&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Nicaraguan non-profit I was working for was set up to improve access to
healthcare for extremely rural communities. The villages they served were very
hard to get to, often requiring multiple days of travel involving 4x4 trucks,
Cessnas and dugout canoes. Conversely, the villagers could expect delays,
substantial risk and great personal expense to get their products to market.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/rural-homestead.jpeg"
alt="A rural family homestead. Chickens on the patio, small fields foregound, jungle backdrop."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>A photogenic rural family homestead in Nicaragua&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The organization I was working for had observed that their best attempts to
improve healthcare access would have only marginal impact unless they also
worked to address some of the underlying reasons for why these villages were
unable to get treatment. One of the most significant factors at play was that
many people simply could not afford even the most subsidized healthcare
treatment. An improvement in the economic prospects of a community would
translate directly into better access to healthcare for that community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to its stable shelf-life, the most common export from a village is rice.
Before it can be cooked, rice must be dehulled. Dehulled rice is more
valuable by weight, so my organization decided to invest some R&amp;amp;D in dehulling
technology that might be feasible in a rural community. A successful technology
could significantly improve a farmer&amp;rsquo;s profitability and, consequently,
healthcare.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/full-grain-rice.jpeg"
alt="A view into a white sack of unprocessed rice."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>A sack of rice before it is dehulled.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="a-prototype">A Prototype&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some villages are not so far from a road or major river and can bring in
gasoline to run a generator occasionally. Others are limited to a community
solar panel to charge a cell phone or a pocket radio, or import power in the
form of AA batteries purchased downriver. Human power, on the other hand, is
readily available.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For small batches of rice, such as for a family meal, it is possible to dehull
rice with a large mortar and pestle, but this ancient tool is unsurprisingly
too slow and exhausting for a farmer to process even their small yields, which
are measured in 25 kg sacks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what if we somehow attached a small commercial rice dehuller to a set of
bike pedals? A reasonably fit human can produce a steady 100 W for one hour on
a bicycle, this was tantalizingly close to the lower power limit on the smallest
commercial rice dehuller we could buy in town. Could we harness human power to
dehull rice efficiently? To answer the question, I was to work on a prototype.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The construction and design of the prototype can be seen in the following photos.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/crankset-and-seatpost-extraction.jpeg"
alt="Using a grinding disc to cut up an old bike frame in a rustic shop"/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Sacrificing a bike frame to extract the crankset and seatpost&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/welderman-at-work.jpeg"
alt="A bike chain connecting the crankset to the flywheel and derailleur."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>A flywheel is constructed by filling the rear wheel with concrete and is mounted ahead of the cranks. The rear derailleur is preserved. In the background, the shop owner casually finishes up some welds.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/flywheel-and-seatpost-mounted.jpeg"
alt="The whole machine is visible on the workbench, but in a partially assembled state."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>On the other side of the flywheel, a pully is embedded into the concrete. This will be used to transfer power from the flywheel to the dehuller.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/bicitrilladora-flywheel-closeup.jpeg"
alt="Iron bars are bent into a circle and welded together and then welded to bolts embetted in the flywheel."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>A closeup of the flyweel and the home-made pully.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/bicitrilladora-painted-testing.jpeg"
alt="The fully assembled machine, painted blue with a green dehuller mounted. A belt connects the flywhel to the dehuller."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Painted and fully assembled, with the commercial dehuller mounted. The dehuller mount is slotted to set the belt tension. Unprocessed rice goes into the hopper at the top and out the shute on the side into the sack.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="results">Results&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Once assembled, the prototype was delivered to a rural community for testing. A
lot of people enjoyed using the machine, almost equally as a way to show off
how fast they could pedal as to extract the rice itself. Pedalling the
bicitrilladora was not at all unlike spin class, and a few operators would be
able to process a sack of rice in under two hours, much faster and easier than
the traditional method.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/mostly-dehulled-rice.jpeg"
alt="A cup of poorly dehulled rice."/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Rice from early in testing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>It took a bit of practice to operate the dehuller itself. Common issues were
broken grains and grains still in the hull, as seen in the picture. Ultimately,
I don&amp;rsquo;t think any more of this machine was made, however in my mind the
limiting factor was not the pedal-power but rather the rather finicky commercial
dehuller that we were using. Even so, the bicitrilladora was still viewed as
preferable by many users over the traditional pounding method.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>raising fish in my college basement</title><link>https://vdwees.github.io/post/fry-to-fried/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vdwees.github.io/post/fry-to-fried/</guid><description>
&lt;p>While in my last year of university, I became obsessed with the idea of having
my own micro aquaponics ecosystem. Then, in a moment of weakness, I bought
fifteen tilapa fry on eBay.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I was introduced to aquaponics by my neighbor, Jed. Aquaponics fascinated me
because it you can think of it as a miniature ecosystem, complete with its own
nutrient cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To those unfamiliar, an &lt;em>aquaponics&lt;/em> system combines two high-density farming
techniques: &lt;em>aquaculture&lt;/em> and &lt;em>hydroponics&lt;/em>. Aquaculture is raising fish, and
hydroponics is growing plants with nutrient-rich water instead of soil. In
aquaponics, the basic idea is:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>the farmer feeds the fish&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the dirty fish water feeds the plants&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the fish and plants feed the farmer&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>In some ways, an aquaponics system is similar to the famous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biosphere_2">Biosphere
2&lt;/a> experiment. Jed was eager to give
hydroponics a try, and suggested we give it a go together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One day, while walking home, I spotted a couple small glass aquariums someone
left on the side of the road. I carried them home (with the owner&amp;rsquo;s blessing)
and set them on Jed&amp;rsquo;s desk. It was a nice warm summer evening and several beers
later, I found myself on eBay searching for fish. Turns out, there are people
on eBay who will mail you live fish. I woke up to this email:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Your order has been sent Monday. 2 day priority. I will have tracking listed.
Be watching for your fish, so they are not left outside long after delivered.
To hot to cold. Also just wanted you to be aware of common mistakes. Don&amp;rsquo;t put
in with other bigger fish or they will be eaten. Make sure intake/filter is
small enough that they don&amp;rsquo;t get sucked in or they will die. This may seem
obvious, but it has happened to customers before. Just want to protect your
investment the best I can. You will want to acclimate the fish 20 min. In bag
in tank when they arrive, just to help adjust them to temp. change. Feed them
crushed flake food. Any other questions, or problems please ask.
Thanks, Brad&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="the-girls">The Girls&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Jed was thrilled, of course. The fish stayed on his desk initially, and in
short order he took to calling them his &amp;ldquo;girls&amp;rdquo;. The &amp;ldquo;girls&amp;rdquo; were blue tilapia,
which according to my research were a pretty hardy bunch. This turned out to be
true- all 15 that I bought survived and thrived despite my many mistakes in
caring for them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fish continued to grow quickly. Up to this point, they were merely
decorative, but the farmers were getting hungry. Below is a photo of the fish
once they were first moved to a larger tank in my basement. At this point they
are about five times larger than how they arrived. Shortly after this photo was
taken, I converted our aquarium into a hydroponics system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/small-fish.jpeg" alt="The fish, finger-sized, in a full-size tank">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-lettuce">The Lettuce&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are many techniques to grow plants without soil. One of the easiest ones
is the floating bed approach. The plants are embedded into a floating structure
and their roots are allowed to dangle into the nutrient-laden water below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a sketch of a basic setup. The water from the fish tank is cycled
though the floating bed, flowing in from the right and exiting on the left.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/floating-bed.png" alt="Hand sketch of a floating bed for growing lettuce">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose to plant lettuce in my basement. Lettuce, while not as valuable as
other greens that may be found growing in a basement, have the advantages of
growing really well on a floating bed setup and are unquestionably legal to
posses. The newly germinated and planted lettuce plants are pictured below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/baby-lettuce.jpeg" alt="Newly germinated lettuce planted in a floating bed">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few weeks, the lettuce was really growing nicely, as shown in the next
photo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/bigger-lettuce.jpeg" alt="Lettuce half-way to full size">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t have a picture of them at full-size, but they were very similar to what
you&amp;rsquo;d see in a grocery store and I got a few salads out of them.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>