<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>vdwees.github.io</title><link>https://vdwees.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on vdwees.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vdwees.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>raising fish in my college basement</title><link>https://vdwees.github.io/post/fry-to-fried/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vdwees.github.io/post/fry-to-fried/</guid><description>
&lt;p>While in my last year of university, I became obsessed with the idea of having
my own micro aquaponics ecosystem. Then, in a moment of weakness, I bought
fifteen tilapa fry on eBay.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I was introduced to aquaponics by my neighbor, Jed. Aquaponics fascinated me
because it you can think of it as a miniature ecosystem, complete with its own
nutrient cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To those unfamiliar, an &lt;em>aquaponics&lt;/em> system combines two high-density farming
techniques: &lt;em>aquaculture&lt;/em> and &lt;em>hydroponics&lt;/em>. Aquaculture is raising fish, and
hydroponics is growing plants with nutrient-rich water instead of soil. In
aquaponics, the basic idea is:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>the farmer feeds the fish&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the dirty fish water feeds the plants&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the fish and plants feed the farmer&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>In some ways, an aquaponics system is similar to the famous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biosphere_2">Biosphere
2&lt;/a> experiment. Jed was eager to give
hydroponics a try, and suggested we give it a go together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One day, while walking home, I spotted a couple small glass aquariums someone
left on the side of the road. I carried them home (with the owner&amp;rsquo;s blessing)
and set them on Jed&amp;rsquo;s desk. It was a nice warm summer evening and several beers
later, I found myself on eBay searching for fish. Turns out, there are people
on eBay who will mail you live fish. I woke up to this email:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Your order has been sent Monday. 2 day priority. I will have tracking listed.
Be watching for your fish, so they are not left outside long after delivered.
To hot to cold. Also just wanted you to be aware of common mistakes. Don&amp;rsquo;t put
in with other bigger fish or they will be eaten. Make sure intake/filter is
small enough that they don&amp;rsquo;t get sucked in or they will die. This may seem
obvious, but it has happened to customers before. Just want to protect your
investment the best I can. You will want to acclimate the fish 20 min. In bag
in tank when they arrive, just to help adjust them to temp. change. Feed them
crushed flake food. Any other questions, or problems please ask.
Thanks, Brad&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="the-girls">The Girls&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Jed was thrilled, of course. The fish stayed on his desk initially, and in
short order he took to calling them his &amp;ldquo;girls&amp;rdquo;. The &amp;ldquo;girls&amp;rdquo; were blue tilapia,
which according to my research were a pretty hardy bunch. This turned out to be
true- all 15 that I bought survived and thrived despite my many mistakes in
caring for them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fish continued to grow quickly. Up to this point, they were merely
decorative, but the farmers were getting hungry. Below is a photo of the fish
once they were first moved to a larger tank in my basement. At this point they
are about five times larger than how they arrived. Shortly after this photo was
taken, I converted our aquarium into a hydroponics system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/small-fish.jpeg" alt="The fish, finger-sized, in a full-size tank">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-lettuce">The Lettuce&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are many techniques to grow plants without soil. One of the easiest ones
is the floating bed approach. The plants are embedded into a floating structure
and their roots are allowed to dangle into the nutrient-laden water below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a sketch of a basic setup. The water from the fish tank is cycled
though the floating bed, flowing in from the right and exiting on the left.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/floating-bed.png" alt="Hand sketch of a floating bed for growing lettuce">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose to plant lettuce in my basement. Lettuce, while not as valuable as
other greens that may be found growing in a basement, have the advantages of
growing really well on a floating bed setup and are unquestionably legal to
posses. The newly germinated and planted lettuce plants are pictured below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/baby-lettuce.jpeg" alt="Newly germinated lettuce planted in a floating bed">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a few weeks, the lettuce was really growing nicely, as shown in the next
photo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://vdwees.github.io/images/bigger-lettuce.jpeg" alt="Lettuce half-way to full size">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t have a picture of them at full-size, but they were very similar to what
you&amp;rsquo;d see in a grocery store and I got a few salads out of them.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>